Papers of Peter Wild 1989-2004
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Peter Wild 1989-2004
MS 389
Wild, Peter
The Papers of Peter Wild consist of research conducted by Wild which explores the life and accomplishments of author,John C. Van Dyke
7 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to this collection.
Furhter accruals are expected
Biographical Note
Peter Wild is a noted writer of poetry and nonfiction prose. Wild is well-known for his literary works such as Cochise and Easy Victory. His poems have been published in numerous magazines, which include Ironwood, Chicago Review, and The American Poetry Review. Over the last decade Wild has become the foremost authority on John C. Van Dyke and the Mojave Desert. His contributions to this field include Daggett: Life in a Mojave Frontier Town; The White Heart of Mojave: an Adventure with the Outdoors of the Desert; and John C. Van Dyke: The Desert. Peter Wild has been a professor of English and Creative Writing at the University of Arizona since 1971.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series
Research Materials 1989-2004
Scope and Content Note
Collection consists of research conducted by Peter Wild which explores the life and accomplishments of John C. Van Dyke, author of The Desert. The collection is comprised of Peter Wild’s interviews, notes, correspondence, photographs, research, and poetry on Van Dyke and the Mojave Desert. The collection is organized chronologically by year. Within each year’s addendum the original order created by Wild has been maintained.
Access Terms
Wild, Peter,1940-Archives.
Wild, Peter,1940-Poetry.
Van Dyke, John Charles,1856-1932.
Austin, Mary-Correspondence.
Powell, Lawrence Clark,1906-Research.
Perkins, Edna Brush..
Van Dyke family-Genealogy.
Daggett (Calif.)
Southwest, New-Description and travel.
Deserts--Southwest, New --Description and travel.
Container List
- Series I: 1989
  1989 begins the first year of extensive research conducted by Wild on Van Dyke. It includes the forward for the project, outlining the reasoning and methods behind Wild’s research. The first document and the subsequent addenda include interviews and notes regarding Renee S. House, director of the Gardner A. Sage Library at the New Brunswick Theological Seminary, John W. Beardslee, Professor Emeritus at the New Brunswick Theological Seminary, and an interview conducted with Philip L. Strong, Esq., the second cousin of John C. Van Dyke. Includes Wild’s notes to himself regarding his published and unpublished manuscripts on Van Dyke and an epilogue.
  This Collection is organized into one series: Research materials, 1989-, chronologically arranged.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke "January 2-6, 1989" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1989 Addendum April 8, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Peter Wild’s note to himself, 1989 Addendum April 8, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series I: 1990
  The 1990 addendum sequence contains updated information on Wild’s Van Dyke research and his publications on Van Dyke for the first year. Also included are notes on Van Dyke in relation to his Reformed Church background and his Dutch heritage.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1990 Addendum March 15, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1990 Addendum March 15, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series I: 1991
  Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1990 Addendum
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1990 Addendum January 28, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1990 Addendum July 16, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series I: 1992
  The 1992 addendum sequence includes updated information regarding the publication of John C. Van Dyke’s autobiography and publications by Peter Wild. Detailed Van Dyke family information is also present. Notes also detail Van Dyke’s faked public image and background information on The Brides of Christ. Bibliography included.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1992 Addendum February 26, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1992 Addendum August 30, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series I: 1993
  Included in the 1993 addendum sequence is the publication status of the Van Dyke autobiography and Van Dyke research conducted by others. Article, The Trip Not Taken and responses are also included.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1992 Addendum May 20, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Journal of Arizona History: The Trip Not Taken: John C. Van Dyke, Heroic Doer or Armchair Seer? Spring 1993" (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1993 Addendum. Research Documents (Including correspondence) April-May 1993 "April-May 1993" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - John C. Van Dyke: Our First Politically Correct Desert Writer. No date (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series I: 1994
  This 1994 addendum includes: Mary Austin correspondence, Lawrence Clark Powell notes on Van Dyke, updated Van Dyke notes, information on the faked trip article, and the publication status of Van Dyke’s autobiography, Wild’s first trip to Daggett (location of Van Dyke’s brothers’ ranch), notes on Van Dyke’s references to Dwarf Deer, and attachments including correspondence and research documents. Contains a table of contents.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1994 Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-262 August 30-31, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1994 Addendum (Pt.2) pg. 263 and attachments August 30-31, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series I: 1995
  The 1995 addendum includes information on Theodore Strong Van Dyke and his son Dix, John C. Van Dyke’s older brother and nephew, including John C. Van Dyke’s trips to their ranch in Daggett. Also included is information on Peter Wild’s 1st, 2nd, and 3rd trips to Daggett and his trip to La Jolla. Included is a table of contents and bibliography.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Addendum February 1, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Addendum: Appendix: First Trip to Daggett Photographs, May 28-June 2, 1994 February 1, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Addendum: Appendix: First Trip to Daggett Photographs, May 28-June 2, 1994 February 1, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Part I Addendum (Pt.1) pgs.1-159 December 31,1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Part I Addendum (Pt.2) pgs.160-296 December 31, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Part I Addendum, Appendix: Trip to La Jolla Photographs May 8-11, 1995 December 31, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Part 2 Addendum December 31, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1995 Part 2 Addendum, Appendix: Third Trip to Daggett Photographs, December 21-27, 1995 December 31, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series I: 1996
  The 1996 addendum includes Dix Van Dyke’s papers, Peter Wild’s fourth trip to Daggett and his second trip to La Jolla. It also includes information on the relationships between John C. Van Dyke and Peter Barker, Mary Austin, Mexico, and his brother Theodore. Includes a table of contents and bibliography.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1996 Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-160 December 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1996 Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 161-349 December 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1996 Addendum, Appendix: Fourth Trip to Daggett Photographs, May 6-10, 1996 December 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1996 Addendum, Appendix: Second Trip to La Jolla Photographs, June 12-16, 1996 December 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1996 Addendum, Appendix: John C. Van Dyke and La Noria Verde, Mexico Photographs, August 1996 December 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1996 Addendum, Appendix: Sage Library, New Brunswick Theological Seminary, and other sources Photographs, November 1996 December 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1996 Addendum, Appendix: Trip to Goffs Photographs, December 25-30, 1996 December 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series I: 1997
  The 1997 Sequence: The first addendum includes Peter Wild’s fifth trip to Daggett, information on John C. Van Dyke, Mexico, and Pittsburgh. Contains a comparison of inaccuracies in various reprints of The Desert as well as notes by Lawrence Clark Powell on the 1918 edition of The Desert. The second addendum includes more John C. Van Dyke correspondence, mapping of Theodore Van Dyke’s ranch in Daggett, Wild’s sixth trip to Daggett, and more information on May Beal. Both parts include a table of contents and a bibliography along with research documents and photographs.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1997 Part I Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-143 June 12, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1997 Part I Addendum (Pt.2) pgs. 144-136 June 12, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1997 Part I Addendum, Appendix: Fifth Trip to Daggett (and Goffs) Photographs June 12, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1997 Part I Addendum, Appendix: John C. Van Dyke and Mexico Photographs June 12, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1997 Part II Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1- 240 January 6, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1997 Part II Addendum (Pt.2) pgs. 241-422, includes attachments January 6, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1997 Part II Addendum, Appendix: Frank Thompson, Sixth Trip to Daggett, and Mary Beal Photographs January 6, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series I: 1998
  The 1998 Sequence includes continuing research and correspondence regarding John C. Van Dyke, and a transcription of Recollections of Boy Hood Days in San Diego 1880-1995 by Dix Van Dyke. Also included is Sequence I and II, which contains numerous poems created by Peter Wild. Both sections of the 1998 addendum have a table of contents, bibliography, research documents, and photographs.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1998 Part I Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-203 June 6, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1998 Part I Addendum (Pt.2) pgs. 204-407 June 6, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1998 Part I Addendum, Appendix A-B: Includes Research Documents and Seventh Trip to Daggett Photographs June 6, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1998 Part II Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-204 January 6, 1999> (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1998 Part II Addendum (Pt.2) pgs 205-425 January 6, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1998 Part II Addendum, Appendix: A-B: Includes Research Documents and Eighth Trip to Daggett Photographs January 6, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series I: 1999
  Included is updated information of John C. Van Dyke, Daggett, and projects, information on Edna Brush Perkins author of The White Heart of the Mojave, and Peter Wild’s poetry Sequence I, II, and III. The table of contents, bibliography, and appendix can be found in both Part I and Part II of the Addendum.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part I Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-236 May 24, 1999> (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part I Addendum (Pt.2) pgs. 237-457 May 24, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part I Addendum, Appendix A: W.S. Van Dyke’s The Lady of Daggett motion picture, 1918 May 24, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part I Addendum, Appendix B: Ninth Trip to Daggett Photographs May 24, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part I Addendum, Appendix C: Research Documents (Includes Correspondence) May 24, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part II Addendum January 4, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part II Addendum, Appendix A: Bodie Ghost Town Frozen in Time and Death Valley Memories motion pictures January 4, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part II Addendum, Appendix B: Research Documents (Pt.1) January 4, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part II Addendum, Appendix B: Research Documents (Pt.2) January 4, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part II Addendum, Appendix C: Jane’s Second House in Tucson (Includes Photographs) January 4, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part II Addendum, Appendix C: Lenora Helsom Photographs January 4, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 1999 Part II Addendum, Appendix C: Tenth Trip to Daggett Photographs January 4, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series I: 2000
  This addendum includes more information on John C. Van Dyke, Daggett, and Edna Brush Perkins as well as information on Wild’s trip to Smith River, and his 11th and 12th trip to Daggett. The poem sequence III and IV are included. Addendum 2000 contains a table of contents, bibliography, and appendixes.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2000 Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-167 January 4, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2000 Addendum (Pt.2) pgs. 168-344 January 4, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2000 Addendum, Appendix A: Vital and Research Documents (Include Correspondence) (Pt.1) January 4, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2000 Addendum, Appendix A: Vital and Research Documents (Include Correspondence) (Pt.1) January 4, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2000 Addendum, Appendix A: Vital and Research Documents (Includes Correspondence) (Pt.2) January 4, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2000 Addendum, Appendix B: Smith River, Eleventh, and Twelfth Trips to Daggett Photographs January 4, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series I: 2001
  This addendum contains updated information on John C. Van Dyke, Daggett, and Edna Brush Perkins, a discussion of the Second Trip to Smith River and the 15th Trip to Daggett, poetry by Peter Wild in sequence IV and a table of contents, bibliography, and appendixes.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2001 Addendum January 4, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2001 Addendum, Appendix A: Research Documents (Includes Correspondence) January 4, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2001 Addendum, Appendix B: Fourteenth Trip to Daggett Photographs January 4, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2001 Addendum, Appendix B: Fifteenth Trip to Daggett and John C. Van Dyke Exhibit at Special Collections Photographs January 4, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2001 Addendum, Appendix B: Miscellaneous Photographs January 4, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series I: 2002
  Included is updated information on John C. Van Dyke, Daggett, and Edna Brush Perkins. Notes regarding the 16th and 17th trips to Daggett are also included. Peter Wild’s poetry, Sequence IV continues in this addendum. Addendum 2002 also contains a table of contents, bibliography, and appendixes.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2002 Addendum January 10, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2002 Addendum, Appendix A: Warren’s Well Dedication Ceremony video, May 5, 2002 January 10, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2002 Addendum, Appendix A: Marshall South Family on Ghost Mountain video, February 15, 2003 January 10, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2002 Addendum, Appendix A: Possum Trot video, February 23, 2003 January 10, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2002 Addendum, Appendix B: Research Documents (Includes Correspondence) (Pt.1) January 10, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2002 Addendum, Appendix B: Research Documents (Includes Correspondence) (Pt.2) January 10, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2002 Addendum, Appendix C: Sixteenth and Seventeenth Trips to Daggett Photographs January 10, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series I: 2003
  This addendum contains: updated materials on John C. Van Dyke, Daggett, and Edna Brush Perkins, notes regarding the 18th trip to Daggett and a trip to Palm Springs, and Wild’s poetry, Sequence IV. Addendum 2003 also contains a table of contents, bibliography, and Appendixes, A-E. Appendix A chiefly includes correspondence and photocopied newspaper clippings. The majority of the correspondence includes email communication between Ann Jopenga and Peter Wild. Appendix B, Part 1 and 2 include Ann Jopenga’s notes on L.A. Times article of January 6, 2002, her notes regarding Marshall South, and her interview with Rider South in 2001. Appendix C includes a movie on CD of Marshall South’s family around 1945/46. Appendix D includes information on the Historic Daggett Garage and corresponding photographs taken on May 2, 2003. Appendix E includes photos from the 18th trip to Daggett May 11-21, 2003 and photographs from a trip to Palm Springs on December 19-27, 2003.
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum (Pt.1) pgs. 1-129. January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum (Pt. 2) pgs 130-240. January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum, Appendix A: Research Documents (includes correspondence) (Pt. 1). January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum, Appendix A: Research Documents (includes correspondence) (Pt. 2). January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum, Appendix B: Ann Jopenga’s notes (Pt.1). January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum, Appendix B: Ann Jopenga’s notes (Pt. 2). January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum, Appendix C: CD movie of the Marshall South Family. January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum, Appendix D: Historic Daggett Garage (includes photographs). January 5, 2004> (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Interviews and Notes Regarding John C. Van Dyke, 2003 Addendum, Appendix E: 18th trip to Daggett and trip to Palm Springs. January 5, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)